Finding Aid for the Michael J. A. Doran Research Papers, 1975-1978
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
Michael J. A. Doran Research Papers, 1975-1978
Mus. Arc. 37
Doran, Michael John Arthur, 1940-1978
4 boxes (50 folders)
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
The collection contains research notes, journal articles, and copies of source materials collected 1975-1978. The focus of the research is music by Alessandro Stradella (1644-1682) and Carlo Ambrogio Lonati (circa 1656-circa 1710-15) and other 17th century Italian composers.
Administrative Information
Terms of Access
Materials can be examined by qualified researchers in the Music Library during hours of operation during which Music Librarians are present. In order to insure access, researchers are advised to contact the Music Library in advance of visits.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Eve Harwood, circa 1980.
Accruals and Additions
No further accruals are expected to this collection.
Biographical Note
Michael Doran was born to Marion and Arthur Doran in Hamilton Ontario in 1940. He was the oldest of their four children. The family lived in the nearby town of Dundas, Ontario, where Michael attended primary and secondary school, and studied piano privately. He earned an Associate Diploma in Piano Performance from the Royal Conservatory of Toronto while an undergraduate at McMaster University in Hamilton, Ontario, where he received his undergraduate degree in English Literature. Upon graduation he won a major scholarship to do graduate work in music history at the University of Chicago. His musical mentor at McMaster was Professor Frank Thorolfson, who had taught at the University of Chicago before moving to McMaster to establish its Bachelor of Music degree program and become its first Music chair.
While completing his master's thesis in musicology at the University of Chicago Michael taught a year at Dickinson College in Carlyle, Pennsylvania, then returned to the Dundas, Ontario area where he was active as a church organist, choral director, and piano teacher for several years. During this time he also served as adjunct music professor at McMaster and as choral director for the music department's newly established choir Schola Cantorum. He received his Master of Music degree from the University of Chicago in 1975. The title of his thesis was The Trio Sonatas of Alessandro Stradella. In 1975 he enrolled in the doctoral program in musicology at the State University of New York at Buffalo. While there he also studied harpsichord and directed a vocal ensemble for early music, the Collegium Musicum, similar to one he had begun at the University of Chicago when in the graduate program there. Michael's research for his doctoral dissertation focused on the life and works of Carlo Ambrogio Lonati (circa 1645-circa 1710-1715). It was a logical extension of his fascination with 17th century Italian music and the research he had done for his Master’s thesis concerning Lonati's colleague, Alessandro Stradella (1639-1682). His research on Lonati resulted in the publication of his biographical entry for Lonati in the New Grove Dictionary of Music and Musicians, 1980. Michael J. A. Doran passed away in March 1978.
Biographical information courtesy of Michael J. A. Doran's wife, Dr. Eve Harwood.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains research notes, journal articles, and copies of source materials collected 1975-1978. The focus of the research is the music of Alessandro Stradella (1644-1682) and Carlo Ambrogio Lonati (circa 1656-circa 1710-15) and other 17th-century Italian composers. The research was intended to result in a Ph.D. dissertation on Lonati but was never completed. It includes photocopies of Owen Jander's research on Lonati's vocal music, correspondence between Jander, Doran, and the editors of the New Grove Dictionary of Music and Musicians, 1980 edition, regarding Doran's article on Lonati. It also contains photocopies of 17th century music manuscripts and published scores relevant to Stradella and Lonati.
One third of the collection consists of negative and positive photocopies of music manuscripts from Italian libraries. One fifth of the collection consists of positive photocopies of journal articles and selections from monographs. Some of the photoprints from microfilms have faded to the extent that they are no longer legible. Fortunately, the library holds microfilms from which the prints were made.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in two series:
I. Sources
II. Research
Container List
- Sources, 1679-1840, I.; Folder 1-16
  - Bologna. Civico Museo Bibliografico Musicale. Ms. Mart. 6.1 (V.195). Excerpt, circa 1840, 3 pages, positive photoprint from microfilm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    f. 87-88v. Lonati. La fortuna fa la ruota. Duet.
    Available on microfilm in the library: MicFilm MIC_1 M02 L841 f
  - London. British Museum. Ms. Harley 1863. Excerpts, undated, 28 leaves, faded negative photoprint from microfilm. Some pages illegible. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    f. 82-90. Lonati(but possibly Cesti or Cazzati). Nel adirato seno. Aria for voice and basso continuo.
    f. 187-190. Lonati. Gite pur l'aria. Aria for voice and basso continuo.
    f. 281-290. Lonati? Nel adirato seno. Aria for voice and basso continuo. A different setting from f. 82.
    Index to Ms. Harley 1863.
    Available as microfilm in the library: MIC_1 M02 A3 Lbm (h.1863)
  - Modena. Biblioteca Estense. Ms. Mus. F.639. Complete, circa 1686, 3 leaves, faded positive photoprint from microfilm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Lonati. Sonata in A major for violin and basso continuo.
    Available on microfilm in the library: MicFilm MIC_1 M02 L841 so
    Available in digital format at: Biblioteca Estense Universitaria, Biblioteca digitale - Musicali (Music works)
  - Modena. Biblioteca Estense. Ms. Mus. F.1372. Excerpts, undated, 37 pages, badly faded positive photoprint from microfilm. Most pages illegible. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    f. 1-18v.
    Available on microfilm in the library: MicFilm MIC_1 M02 A3 MOe (F.1372)
  - Modena. Biblioteca Estense. Ms. Mus. F.1383. Excerpts, undated, 12, 19 pages, positive photoprint from microfilm (Box 1, Folder 5)
    f. 17-26. Lonati. I teneri lamenti di Filli abbandonata. Cantata for soprano and basso continuo.
    f. 27-38v. Lonati. Naviganti al lido. Cantata for two voices and basso continuo.
    Available on microfilm in the library: MicFilm MIC_1 M02 L841 ca
  - Modena. Biblioteca Estense. Ms. Mus. F.1549. Excerpts, 1686, 51, faded positive photoprint from microfilm (Box 1, Folder 6)
    All from: Lonati. I due germani rivali (1686). Opera.
    f. 1-14; 24v-26; 46-48; 138-140v; 142-146.
    Available on microfilm in the library: MicFilm MIC_1 M02 L841 d
  - Modena. Biblioteca Estense. Ms. Mus. G.111. Excerpts, undated, 24 pages, badly faded positive photoprint from microfilm. Some pages illegible. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    No. 1. Lonati. Al ferio. Aria for alto and basso continuo. No. 14. Lonati. Ni fa piangere. Aria for soprano and basso continuo.
    No. 34. Lonati. Annodami abbracciami. Aria for soprano and basso continuo.
    No. 40. Lonati. Se non ardo. Aria for soprano and basso continuo.
    Available on microfilm in the library under title, Ariette a vocî diverse e duettino con basso continuo: MicFilm MIC_1 M02 L841 ar
  - Modena. Biblioteca Estense. Ms. Mus. G.112. Complete, undated, 36 pages, faded positive photoprint from microfilm. Some pages illegible. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Lonati. Solca il mar da rie tempeste. Cantata for soprano solo and basso continuo.
    Available on microfilm in the library: MicFilm MIC_1 M02 St786 so
    Available in digital format at Biblioteca Estense Universitaria, Biblioteca digitale - Musicali (Music works)
  - Turin. Biblioteca nazionale. Ms. Giordano 15. Excerpts, undated, 3, 12, 17 pages, faded positive photoprint from microfilm. Some pages illegible (Box 1, Folder 9)
    f. 79v-87v. Lonati. Trio sonata in D. major for 2 violins and basso continuo.
    f. 103-108v. Lonati. Trio sonata in C major for 2 violins and basso continuo.
    2 pages incipits for f. 58-108, in Doran's hand. Notes in margin.
    Available on microfilm in the library under the title, Sinfonia del Lelio Colista et altri: MicFilm MIC_2 M02 A3 Tn (g.15)
  - Scelta di canzonette italiane de piu autori. Dedicate a gli a della musica. Printed at London, by A. Godbid and J. Playford, in Little Britain, 1679. Excerpts, 1679, 28 pages, faded negative photoprint from microfilm (Box 1, Folder 10)
    p. 37-42. Lonati. Tu partisti idolo amato. Aria for soprano and basso continuo.
    p. 81-84. Lonati (but possibly Mannelli or Caproli). Voglio morte e voglio vita. Aria for soprano and basso continuo. p. 102-108. Stradella. Non a mai amor ferir. Duet for 2 sopranos and basso continuo. p. 109-116. Stradella. Care labbra. Duet for 2 sopranos and basso continuo.
    Available on microfilm in the library: MicFilm M72019 A3 P626 s
  - Transcription in Doran's hand, of Lonati's Tu partisti idolo amato, pages 37-42 from Scelta di canzonette italiane de piu autori undated, 3 pages manuscript music (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Select preludes and vollentarys for the violin, being made and contrived for the improvement of the hand with variety of compositions by all the greatest masters in Europe. London, printed for J. Walsh... and J. Hare at the Golden Viol in St. Paul's Churchyard. Complete, circa 1705, 41 pages, faded positive photoprint from microfilm (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Includes works by Lonati, Cosma, A. Corelli, Torelli, Purcell and others.
    Available in digital format in International Music Score Library Project (IMSLP)
  - Select preludes and volluntarys for the flute, being made and contriv'd for ye improvement of ye hand with variety of compositions by all the eminent masters in Europe. London, printed for J. Walsh and Randall and J. Hare. Complete, 1708, 18 pages, faded positive photoprint from microfilm (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Available on microfilm in the library: MIC-1 M317 A3 se
  - Armonie di Pindo: Cantate da camera a voce sola di diversa eccellenti autori nuovamente raccolte, e date in luce da Federico Vigoni e dal medemo consacrate al grano merito del M. R. Padre D. Claudio Antonio Strada. Milano. Complete, 1712, 181 pages reproduced 4 pages to 1 leaf, faded positive photoprint from microfilm (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Available on microfilm in the library: MicFilm | MIC-1 M715 A3 V68 ar
  - Cialli, Rinaldo. Ariberto e Flavio, regi de Longobardi, |dramma per musica; da rappresentarsi nel ristaurato famoso Teatro Vendramino di San Salvatore, l'anno MDCLXXXV. Venice: Francesco Nicolini, 1684, 69 pages printed 2 per leaf, badly faded positive photoprint from microfilm. Some pages illegible.; Libretto to opera by Carlo Ambrogio Lonati. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Available on microfilm in the library: MicFilm MIC_1 ML1498
  - D'Averara, Pietro. L'Aiace. Dramma per musica. Da rappresentarsi nil Regio Teatro di Milano l'anno 1694. In Milano, Carlo Federico Gagliard. Seconda Impressione. Excerpts, 1697, 14 leaves, Photocopy (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Incomplete libretto. Includes only introductory pages and no text.
    Available on microfilm in the library: MicFilm MIC_1 ML1496
    Available in digital format at Museo internazionale e biblioteca della musica di bologna
- Research, 1673-1978, II.; Folder 17-50
  Photocopies of articles
  - Photocopies of dictionary articles on Alessandro Stradella with accompanying notes and translations, undated, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Authors include Fétis, Sartori, Schmidl, Grove, Pirrotta, and Michel.
  - Notes on Alessandro Stradella and the topic of rhythm in Baroque music, quoted from dictionaries, monographs and journals, undated, 13 leaves (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Bourdelot, Pierre and Pierre Bonnet. Histoire de la musique et ses effets (Paris, 1715): pages 41-45 and 59-67. 1966, 1969, 12 leaves, photocopies (Box 2, Folder 19)
    A discussion of Stradella's music.
  - Richard, P. Stradella et les Contarini, in Le Ménestral, 1865-1866, 37 leaves, photocopies (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Article about Stradella issued in parts from November 18 1865 through April 1 1866. Missing issue of December 31 1865.
  - Gatti, Guido M. Current Chronicle in Musical Quarterly 36: pages 124-130. A review of Stradella's oratorio San Giovanni Battista, 1950, 4 leaves, photocopies (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Altmann, Wilhelm. Kammermusik-Katalog: ein Verzeichnis von seit 1841 veröffentlichten Kammermusikwerken, sechste bis August 1944 ergänzte Auflage (Hofheim am Taunus, 1944): pages 74-75, 170-71, and 242-43, 1944, 3 leaves, photocopies (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Lists of works by Stradella.
  - Notes on Stradella's contemporaries, including Lonati, Mannelli, and Colista, copied from dictionary articles, in Doran's hand, undated, 2 manuscript leaves (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Miscellaneous notes and journal articles about Queen Christina of Sweden, undated, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Miscellaneous notes and journal articles about the Great Britain Public Records Office, 16874,88, undated, 22 leaves (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Miscellaneous notes and journal articles about Sir Christopher Wren and Whitehall Palace, London, undated, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Miscellaneous notes about 17th century sonatas, in Doran's hand, undated, 5 leaves (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Bononcini, Giovanni Maria. Musico Prattico (Bologna), pages 24-25 and 40 1673, 2 leaves, photocopies (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Brenzoni, R. Giuseppe Torelli, musicista veronese in Note d'archivio per la storia musicale 13: 22-37, 1936, 8 leaves, photocopies (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Smith, Helen Margaret. F. M. Veracini's "Il trionfo della prattica musicale" 1963, 12 leaves, badly faded negative photoprint from microfilm. Almost completely illegible. (Box 2, Folder 30)
    Ph.D. thesis, Indiana University, 1963: pages 122-131 and 220-243. A partial translation and commentary on Veracini's treatise.
    Available on microfilm in the library: MicFilm MIC_1 ML118
  - Miscellaneous notes and journal articles about Lonati, Maggi, and Muratori, undated, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Black ring binder containing miscellaneous notes about Lonati and his contemporaries, in Doran's hand, undated, 1 binder (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Miscellaneous bibliographical notes about Lonati and related topics, in Doran's hand. undated, 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 33)
    Includes manuscript transcription of Benedetto Ferrari's Premo, premoil giogo dell' Alpi (1633).
  - Owen Jander's research on Lonati's vocal music. Includes notes about telephone conversations between Jander and Doran, in Doran's hand, and written correspondence, undated, 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Notes on Lonati's duet La fortuna fa la ruota in: Bologna. Civico Museo Bibliografico Musicale, Ms. Mart. 6.1 (V.195): 57-58v. undated, 6 leaves (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Miscellaneous notes, mostly about the opera L'Aiace by Lonati, Paolo Magni and Francesco Ballarotti, undated, 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Notes about Lonati's cantata I teneri lamenti di Filli abbandonata, undated, 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 37)
    Bassani, Giovanni Battista. L'Amante placata. Cantata for voice and basso continuo. Notes, in pencil, in Doran's hand.
    Transcription of I teneri lamenti di filli abbandonata from Modena. Biblioteca Estense, Ms. Mus. F.1383: 17-26.
  - Notes on sources for Lonati, in Doran's hand, undated, 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Notes on sources for Lonati, in Doran's hand, including excerpts from printed library catalogues, undated, 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Bound notebook with notes about Lonati, undated, 1 notebook (Box 3, Folder 40)
    Includes biography, notes on works and sources, problems and questions, bibliography, and notes on Lonati's contemporaries.
  - Miscellaneous notes and transcriptions, all incomplete, on Lonati, undated, 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Carlo Ambrogio Lonati: life and works, 1975, 17 manuscript leaves (Box 3, Folder 42)
    Ms, in Doran's hand. Draft of the paper for the Fall, 1975 doctoral seminar in music history at SUNY-Buffalo, under the direction of David Fuller.
  - Carlo Ambrogio Lonati: life and works, December 15, 1975, 39 pages (Box 3, Folder 43)
    Two photocopies.
  - Carlo Ambrogio Lonati: life and works, December 15, 1975, 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 44)
    Typescript with additional notes in Doran's hand.
  - Carlo Ambrogio Lonati: life and works, February 1976, 38 pages (Box 3, Folder 45)
    Typescript. Revised version, February 1976. Notes in margin in Doran's hand.
    Accompanied by Un musicista salodiano del Sec. XVII, Carlo Pallavicini in Note d'Archivio, XVIII (1941).
  - Miscellaneous notes on Lonati including biographical outline, 1975-1977, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Correspondence from Michael J. A. Doran to the Biblioteca Apostolica Vaticana about sources for Lonati's works, November 1977, 4 leaves (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Correspondence about Lonati article for New Grove Dictionary of Music, 6th edition, 1976, 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Correspondence about Lonati article for New Grove Dictionary of Music, 6th edition, 1977-1978, 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - St. Edmund's MSS, etc., undated, 1 envelope (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 50)
Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog.
Contributors
Jander, Owen
Subjects
Music--Italy--17th century; Lonati, Carlo Ambrogio; Stradella, Alessandro, 1639-1682
Genres
scores; papers (document genres)